Guide to the Charles S. Sydnor Papers, 1729-1978and undated RL.01273
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1729-1954 (bulk 1923-1954).
  - Writings
    - Reducing the Risks in Politics: Address delivered at the Virginia State Library, 1953, June 12 (Box 10)
    - Reviews: 1931-1949, n.d, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Reviews: (Box 11)
      - 1931-1949, undated, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - 1949-1952, n.d, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Roanoke World News, 1923-1924 (Box 11)
    - Second Thoughts and Suggestions, a contribution to Pennsylvania Conference on American Political History, Pennslyvania Magazine of History and Biography LXXII, 201-202, (Apr. 1948), 1948 (Box 11)
    - A Slave Owner and His Overseers, 1937 (Box 11)
    - Slavery in Mississippi:
      - Background materials, 1790-1932, undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Bowle's Plantation (Mrs. Bem Price), 1850-1851 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence relating to, undated (Box 11)
      - Devlin Diary, 1836-1885 (Box 11)
      - Finney slave trader letters, 1836-1837 (Box 11)
      - Leigh Plantation Account Book, 1852-1853 (Box 11)
      - Leigh Plantation Book, 1852-1933 (Box 11)
      - Reviews, undated (Box 11)
    - The Southern Experiment in Writing Social History, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    - The Southerner and the Laws, 1939, undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - State Geological Surveys in the Old South, 1939-1940 (Box 11)
    - Thomas Jefferson's Comments on the Report of the President's Commission on Higher Education, undated (Box 11)
    - Travels in the Old South:
      - Background materials, 1837-1906, undated (Box 11)
      - Collaborators information, undated (Box 11)
      - Printer's copy with notes, undated, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Unused research, undated (Box 11)
    - Voting in Early America: (Box 12)
      - 1952, undated (Box 12)
      - Illustrations, 1952, undated (Box 12)
    - Wailes, B. L. C.:
      - Address Delivered at... Jefferson College, 1842 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence related to, 1931-1934 (Box 12)
      - Diary of, 1853-1932, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Inaugural Address Delivered at the first meeting of Adams Athenaeum 31 March 1825 (Box 12)
      - Inaugural Address Read at the Historical Society of Mississippi by B.L.C. Wailes and related documents, 1859-1934, n.d (Box 12)
    - What the Historian Expects of an Archival Agency or Historical Society, Society of American Archivists, 1948 (Box 12)
  - Background Materials
    - Crockett Mss.: Slavery and Reconstruction, 1872 (Box 12)
    - Elections:
      - Presidential and state, 1820 (Box 12)
      - Presidential, 1824-1832, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Statistics, 1820-1860 (Box 12)
    - Elizabeth Female Academy (Washington, Miss.), 1936 (Box 12)
    - Estate of James K. Polk: Inventory, 1934 (Box 12)
    - Jefferson College, Washington, Miss., 1936 (Box 12)
    - Justices of the Peace:
      - North Carolina and Kentucky Legislatures, etc., 1820-1940, undated (Box 12)
      - Virginia, 1942-1945, undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Virginia, Justices, Summary sheets, 1820, undated (Box 12)
      - West Virginia, 1820, undated (Box 12)
    - Leadership after 1865, undated (Box 12)
    - Map and election statistics and correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 12)
    - Maps:
      - City populations, 1860, 1936 (Box 12)
      - County populations, 1860, 1936 (Box 12)
    - Natchez Institute, 1934-1935 (Box 12)
    - Non-southern related materials, undated (Box 12)
    - Notes and statistics on social and economic condition, 1819, undated (Box 12)
    - Paine Detected, undated (Box 12)
    - Popular prejudices and the historian, notes and research materials, 1931-1949, undated (Box 12)
    - Religion, Education, Literature, etc., undated (Box 12)
    - The South after 1865, undated (Box 12)
    - South Carolina, 1949, undated (Box 12)
    - South Carolina: Charleston, S.C., undated (Box 12)
    - South Carolina public records, 1729-1748 (Box 12)
    - Southern municipal directories and censuses before 1861, undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Southern municipal ordinances and laws before 1861, undated (Box 12)
    - Southern Planter (Natchez), 1842 (Box 12)
    - Southern political leadership before Jackson (except Virginia), 1946, undated (Box 12)
    - Southern towns:
      - undated (Box 12)
      - Occupations: Memphis, Charleston, S.C., Nashville, Louisville, 1836-1860, undated (Box 12)
    - Southwestern Journal, 1837-1838 (Box 12)
    - Virginia counties, undated (Box 12)
    - Western farmer and gardener, 1934 (Box 12)
    - Woodville Manufacturing Company, 1850-1935 (Box 12)
    - Woodville Republican notes (mostly on poetry), 1847-1848 (Box 12)
    - Yellow fever, copy of letter owned by Mrs. James Andrews, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1878 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1818-1953, undated, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - 13a Microfilm boxes: (Box 13)
      - A Collection of Plays and Poems of the Late Colonel Robert Mumford, 1798 (Box 13)
      - [Mississippi General Assembly Senate Journals, 1830 November-1839 January.] (Box 13)
      - [Commission Book No.1, ca. 1787-1797] (Box 13)
      - [Register of Justices and County Officers, 1780-1822] (Box 13)
      - [Register of Magistrates... 1783-1811] (Box 13)
      - [Register of Magistrates... 1852-1865] (Box 13)
    - 13b Index Cards:
      - Mississippi Session Laws, Mississippi Senate and House, undated (Box 13)
      - Journals, Woodville Republican, undated (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous Mississippi newspapers, undated (Box 13)
    - 13c Index Cards: Notes, undated (Box 13)
    - 13d Writings in American History, notes from, undated (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1951, undated (Box 14)
    - Notes for textbooks, 1924-1930, 8 folders (Box 14)
- Correspondence Series Series, 1926-1956 and undated.
  Primarily correspondence to or from Sydnor concerning his career as a professor and as a historian. Also included are letters addressed to Mrs. Sydnor and some relating to Sydnor family matters. Arranged in chronological order by year.
  - 1926-1956 and undated, 7 folders (Box 15)
- Teaching Files Series, 1923-1954, undated
  Includes recommendations, course notes, class rolls, grade books, and student papers related to Sydnor's teaching posts at Duke University and elsewhere. The recommendations, student papers, and grade books are restricted. Arranged alphabetically, with the restricted files following the non-restricted materials.
  - Duke University, Summer Session, 1952-1953, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Examinations: History course, 1924-1952 (Box 15)
  - History courses, 1937-1954, undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Social and Intellectual Development of the Old South, 1938-1945, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Teaching Load Committee Report, 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1927, undated (Box 15)
  - Restricted
    - Class rolls and grades:
      - Duke University Summer Schools, 1935-1951, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Harvard Summer School, 1952 (Box 15)
      - Institute of Early American History and Culture, undated (Box 15)
      - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1949, Summer (Box 15)
    - Grade books, 1923-1953, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Graduate stipends:
      - 1952-1954, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Acceptances and rejections, 1952 (Box 15)
    - Students:
      - Abbot, William, 1949-1953, undated (Box 15)
      - Braverman, Howard, 1949-1950 (Box 15)
      - Cunningham, Noble E., 1949-1953, undated (Box 15)
      - Gescher, Dieter, 1951-1952 (Box 15)
      - Harris, Robert L., 1949-1953 (Box 15)
      - King, Doris Elizabeth, 1949-1953 (Box 15)
      - Malin, Morton V., 1952 (Box 15)
      - McCain, Paul M., 1949-1950 (Box 15)
      - Oliver, George B., 1949-1954 (Box 15)
      - Petersen, Carsten Brink, 1951 (Box 15)
      - Sisk, Glenn N., 1949-1950 (Box 15)
      - Smith, Clarence McK., 1948-1953 (Box 15)
      - Taylor, Orville W., 1949-1953 (Box 15)
      - Papers, 1942-1953, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - undated (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1933-1971 and undated.
  Chiefly consists of clippings, pictures, and printed material documenting Sydnor's professional affiliations.
  - 1933-1978 and undated (Box 16)
  - Clippings, 1933-1971 (Box 16)
  - Sydnor:
    - Biographical information and pictures, 1947-1955, undated (Box 16)
    - Death, 1954, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - List of publications, 1936-1954, undated (Box 16)
    - Papers while a student:
      - 1920-1945, undated, 5 folders (Box 16)
      - Notebooks [1-17], 1916-1921, undated, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Papers while a student:
      - 1920-1945, undated, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - Article on Sydnor, undated, no author indicated, 1 folder (Box 16)
- Oversize Materials
  - Alphabetical Files, 1871-1953, undated (Box 17)
  - Alphabetical Files, 1927-1953, undated (Box 17)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1820-1946, undated (Box 17)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1835-1952 (Box 17)
  - Teaching Files, 1936-1951 (Box 17)